In this lecture, we will be performing cloud operations in ASP.NET Core app with SQL Server
as database.
Both the ASP.NET Core app and SQL Server will be running from two separate Docker containers.
So this is the architecture of the whole app which will be created by us.
This is the ASP.NET Core MVC app and it will be running from a Docker container and since
it will be a database driven, so it will be connecting with SQL Server database and
SQL Server database will also be running from Docker container.
So there will be two separate containers each for the app and the SQL Server and the app
will perform cloud operations on the database.
These cloud operations as you know are create, read, update and delete operations.
So let's start.
So first of all, I would like to show the link to SQL Server running on a Docker container.
On Google, you should type SQL Server and Docker.
Then you will find the Microsoft Learn website.
You will find Microsoft Learn website and Docker Run containers for SQL Server Online
Next.
This link on this link, there are the commands which you have to run.
You can run the full command of SQL Server.
This is the command which will download the SQL Server 2025 image on your local environment
or local PC and to run this container with the SQL Server 2025 image, you copy this
whole command of Docker Run and you change this MS SQL as a password to your own password
which you would like to keep it strong password and you should follow the SQL Server
default password policy which states that the password should have capital letters and
so much smaller letters at least it should be query letters etc.
So you should keep a strong password then let me show you how to run copy this command
and open command prompt and here you paste this command and as you see it is Docker
Run command and dash is the environment flag makes you to accept the policy of this SQL
Server then another environment variable which states that MS SQL underscore S way
underscore password and then afterward you give your own password a strong password like
this one and after that with dash P you specify their ports mappings 1, 4, 4, 0 is D.
You are the host port and then afterwards 1, 4, 4, 3 is the SQL Server container port 1,
4, 4, 0 you can keep your host port any port of your liking I have kept 1, 4, 4, 0 and
then with dash dash name you specify the container name of the SQL Server it can be anything
then with H flag again you keep the same whatever the container name you also keep the same
thing here and then with dash D is it means the detached mode afterwards this is the Microsoft
container registry image of SQL Server 2005 this is the whole command and then you press
enter it gives unable to find image so it is not finding the SQL Server 2025 image
on my PC locally so it is pulling from Microsoft container registry and since it is around
550 MB so you will have to wait from 5 minutes for it to get completed.
Let us see the Docker desktop and this is the SQL Server image which is downloaded and
on containers you will find SQL Server container by the name my SQL Server is now running
and it contains the SQL Server image 2025 image and the ports are 1, 4, 4, 0 colon 1,
port V3 here 1, 4, 4, 0 is the host port and 1, 4, 3, 3 is the port inside the container
we now connect with the database through Visual Studio on Visual Studio check the view
menu then select SQL Server object explorer through this we will connect with the SQL Server
like D plus icon that says add SQL Server in the connect dialog so let D browse then
on D connection properties add SQL details for SQL name add local host comma 1, 4, 4,
0 1, 4, 4, 0 is default on the host which we added to the dash P flag for authentication
select SQL Server authentication username should be essay in capital letters password
should be the one which we use during running the container
with this option which says remember password database name keep it default in crypt mandatory
and fast trust server certificate make sure you check this option now click the connect
button we are now connected to the database inside the database area we have no databases
right now we will be creating our database soon we now move to sp.net core mbc database
driven app here it is you can download this app from this lecture itself let me explain
quickly how this app works this is a movie library app where movies details can be stored
in the database it contains credit operations enable user to create read update and delete
movie records the movies will be stored on the database running from a docker container
let's see the home controller where we have d create action method which does the creation
of the movies on the database the index action where movies are read from the database
the date action method does the updation of the movie records on the database lastly
there is the delete action method which deletes the movies from the database this is the
movie entity class where there are three properties defined these are id name and actors
these are the razor view files the index.cshtml file which shows all the movies in an
HTML table the create.cshtml file contains deform through which new movies are inserted
to the database lastly there is a update.cshtml razor view file where updation of a movie
is done the movie context.cs file acts as a DB context for this whole app the database
connection string is stored in the app settings.json file located on the root of the
app let's understand the connection string the data source should be d SQL server which
is local host comma 1440 recall 1440 is the host port we added on the docker run command
initial catalog is the database name which can be anything of your choice i have named
my database as movie DB user id should be s a in capital letters and password should be
the same used when running the docker container secure server it's time we run the entity
frame of code migration commands from new get package manager console window the first command
to run is ad dash migration followed by migration name i have named my migration as migration
1 you can name it anything now the migration is created with a migration folder on the application
the migration folder contains migration files that are used to execute demigration
on the database next we run the update dash database command this command applies demigration
and so the database is created ok done let's refresh d database
and you can see the database is created it has one table called movie open this table by
right clicking on it and selecting view data there are no movies right now we will be adding
movies with the app in just a moment let's run the app
this is the app let's create a movie for name add layer window
and actors james t word and grey scally the movie is created they are also the update and delete
buttons next to the movie name let's create another movie expandable three actors
sylvester still on and on all scores in agar i think the spelling is a mistake so let's update
and you can see the date have been done click delete button to delete this movie from the database
now refresh the table you can see there is only one movie because we deleted the second movie
and everything is working properly now we will add container compose support to the app
right click depoject name and select add then select container compose support now on the container
scaffolding options window keep all the default settings and click the ok button docker compose
support is added to the app with docker file along with the docker dash compose project open the
docker dash compose dot yml file here you will see the app is added as a service we will now
add SQL server service to this docker dash compose dot yml file i will be copying and pasting
all the necessary codes here but don't worry all these codes will be available for download
from the lecture itself so this is decode we named the service SQL data its name can be anything
this is the SQL server 2025 image the environments are added which basically sets the SQL password
is strong password and except ula policy the ports are different than the one we used earlier
i am using a different port this time since this instance of SQL server will be different
from the one we used before this SQL server will run from a different container i am using port
1450 for the host and 1433 is the SQL server container port always we also add the port
mappings for the dot net corrupt app so that we can access the app on the browser without the
help of visual studio add this below code discord is the same which we used earlier in the previous
lecture note that we have used the host port nine thousand two this time on app settings dot
JSON file change local host comma or zero to SQL data which is the name of the SQL server service
now we run docker compose commands to build and run the whole app from the directory of the
docker dash compose dot yml file you have to run the two commands the first one is docker dash
compose build this will build the images let's see the docker desktop this is the image of the app
and SQL server now run the docker dash compose up to run the two containers done
now on docker desktop you can see these two containers
now we will have to run the migrations so first open the app settings dot JSON file here change
this data source to local host comma 1450 this is the address of the SQL server which we have
recently started in a docker container and now right click the docker current app and select
set as startup project and on package manager console we will write the commands for migrations
so first delete this previous migrations folder and now type add dash migration migration name
i have kept migration name as migration one you can change it based on your choice next command
is update dash database this will apply the migration okay done the database is created
now we change the app settings to previous ones on connection string change SQL data
set docker dash compose project as startup project
the SQL server and dotnet containers are already running so we don't have to do anything
the SQL server container already has the database added to it through migrations
so we just have to open the app on the browser the address is local host colon 9002
and here the app is working from the docker container
congrats you have successfully created this docker compose task of hosting a dotnet
DB based app from docker containers